There was a time when a meteor flashing through the sky
曾几何时 流星划破天空
struck man with a deep sense of wonder.
予人以惊为天人之感
Even today man's reaction to a meteoric display
即使在今天 人们对流星现象的反应可能会是
is likely to jam the switchboards with reports of imminent invasion from space.
大量打入的紧急太空入侵报告 导致电话交换机堵塞
But as heirs to the knowledge disciplines and apparatus of the Scientific Revolution.
但是作为科学革命后知识学科和仪器的继承人
we are familiar with and at least partially understand the meteoric phenomena.
我们熟悉 并且至少部分理解流星现象
A meteoroid traveling in space outside our atmosphere remains unseen by man
人们看不见在大气层外移动的流星
while the molecules in space are so dispersed.
由于太空中分子分散得如此之远
A collision with them causes no visible effect.
与之碰撞不会有明显的影响
If its trajectory traverses the Earth's atmosphere, it becomes a meteor.
如果它的轨道穿过地球大气层 它会成为一颗流星
Here it begins to collide with more molecules.
在这里它会与更多的分子碰撞
These collisions become more and more frequent
这些碰撞越来越频繁
as the meteor descends into the denser air of lower altitude, causing it to decelerate.
同时流星下降到高度较低的更致密空气中 因而减速
Each collision worth some of the energy of motion into heat energy
每一次碰撞使得一些动能转化为热能
and the heat continues to increase
热量持续增加
until the meteor itself becomes incandescent
直到流星本身变得耀眼
scribing it's visible path through the night sky.
在夜空中划出它显眼的轨迹
Destroyed in the atmosphere by this heating, most meteors present no danger to man.
由于在大气层被热量摧毁 大多数流星不会危及人类
Now and then one is large enough
现在有一个足够大的流星
to survive its passage through the atmosphere to earth.
穿过大气层到达地球
It is then called a meteorite and some are very large indeed.
然后 它被称为陨石 有些确实很大
Dr. Peter Parameter became interested in meteors early in his career.
Peter Parameter 博士在他职业生涯早期对此产生了兴趣
And once wrote a paper titled
而曾经写过一篇题为
A thermal kinetic description of bodies
物体在随机速度和角度下
and passage through a plastic medium of nonlinear density
通过非线性密度的塑料介质
at random velocities and angles
的热动力学描述
which could be just about summed up with this equation.
可以用这个方程来概括
With this equation
有了这个公式
is fellow scientists and designers are able to explain
其他科学家和设计师们能够解释
the effects of atmospheric penetration on differing bodies.
大气穿透对不同物体的影响
Those with different ballistic coefficients at various velocities and angles.
那些各种速度和角度不同的弹道系数
For example, if two bodies of different weights enter the Earth's atmosphere
例如 如果重量不同的两个物体进入地球大气层
with the same velocity and entry angle,
在相同的速度和进入角下
both the heavy body and the light one will begin to heat up at the same time.
重的和轻的物体将同时开始升温
What impacts of air molecules slow the light body sooner.
空气分子的影响会使轻的物体更快变慢
This deceleration of the light body occurs at higher altitudes
轻的物体在更高的高度减速
while the heavier more energetic body penetrates deeper
而更重的能量更多的物体
before it reaches peak deceleration.
在它到最大减速前穿透得更深
The total amount of heat generated by the lighter one
轻的物体产生的总热能
is less than that generated by the heavy one
小于由重的那个产生的
whose larger mass is it greater kinetic energy.
它更大的质量意味着更大的动能
Two identical bodies with the same velocity
以相同速度进入大气层的两个相同物体
entering the atmosphere at different angles also will decelerate at different rates.
在不同的角度下也将以不同的速率减速
The steeper angle causes a more rapid encounter with the dense air
更陡的角度会导致与稠密空气更急促的接触
resulting in more abrupt deceleration.
从而导致更多的突然减速
The total heat generated will be the same for both bodies
两个物体所产生的总热量是相同的
but peak heating will be less for the shallow entry.
但平缓进入的峰值加热会更小
With identical meteors entering at the same angle but with different velocities,
具有相同角度但以不同速度进入的相同流星
the faster meteor under heavier bombardment by air molecules
更快的流星在空气分子更重的轰击下
will have greater deceleration generating more heat and at a higher rate.
会有更快的减速 同时以较高的速率产生更多的热量
But Dr. Parameter is no longer merely an observer
但是Parameter博士已不再仅仅是一个
interested in understanding the phenomena of meteors.
有兴趣了解流星现象的观察者
A meteor is just an aimless traveler in space.
流星只是在太空漫无目的的旅客
Doc finds himself now involved in designs with a purpose and an aim.
博士现在从事设计拥有自己的目标
A missile has a target.
导弹有一个目标
And a spacecraft has a destination, a journey's end.
而航天器有一个目的地 一个旅程的结束
To these Doc applies his knowledge.
在其上博士运用自己的知识
He knows natural phenomena both of aimless meteor and aimed missile.
他知道无目标的流星和有目标的导弹背后的自然现象
He knows that as they traverse the atmosphere they heat up.
他知道 当它们穿过大气层 它们热了起来
If the heating or deceleration of a vehicle is excessive the mission is threatened.
如果飞行器过度加热或减速 任务会受到威胁
Man cannot change the laws of nature.
人不能改变自然规律
So he must use his knowledge to work within those laws.
所以他必须在这规律下运用自己的知识来工作
Dr. Parameter knows that
Parameter博士知道
the two natural enemies to successful atmospheric penetration
成功的大气穿透有两大天敌
are deceleration and heat.
减速和热量
He can fight these enemies on two possible fronts.
他可以在两种可能的方面对抗这些敌人
First on the design front by modifying the vehicle shape and size relative to its weight.
首先在设计方面根据飞行器重量更改其形状和大小
In other words its ballistic coefficient.
换而言之其弹道系数
And second on the program front,
其次在程序方面
by altering the vehicle’s trajectory,
通过改变飞行器的弹道
its velocity, its attitude and its angle of entry into the Earth's atmosphere.
它的速度 它的高度和它进入地球大气层的角度
Dr. Parameter is now ready to use his technology
参Parameter博士现在已经可以运用他的技术
to plan a successful re-entry for an ICBM warhead.
为洲际弹道导弹弹头策划成功的再入
He knows that of the two natural enemies, deceleration and heat.
他知道 这两个天敌 减速和热量
High deceleration is not a problem with a warhead.
高减速对于核弹头来说不是问题
but too much heat could destroy it.
但过多的热量会破坏它
He first surveys the project on the program front.
他首先调查项目的程序部分
He knows that the re-entry velocities and angles are essentially set by the mission.
他知道 再入速度和角度基本上由任务决定
But to reduce heat load, the velocity of the re-entry vehicle
但是 为了减少热负荷 再入大气层飞行器的速度
could theoretically be reduced by firing a retro rocket.
理论上可以通过反推火箭减少
On investigation he finds that
经调查 他发现
in order to decrease for re-entry velocity sufficiently by this method,
为了充分地利用该方法以减少再入速度
a retro thrust system would be required
需要一个反推系统
weighing many times the weight of the warhead.
是数倍于弹头的重量
This method is out.
这种方法出局
He next considers the possibility of changing the re-entry angle.
他接着考虑改变再入角的可能性
He knows that a shallow angle will lessen the peak heat load
他知道 一个小的角度将减少热负荷峰值
by stretching the heating over a longer period of time.
因为这会延长加热的时间
But the total heat generated will be the same either way.
但产生的总热量是相同
And the vehicle could absorb even more heat during this longer re-entry.
而飞行器会在较长的再入过程中吸收更多的热量
Furthermore, a shallow re-entry angle has other serious drawbacks.
此外 较小的再入角有其他严重缺陷
First a shallow angle impairs accuracy by deflection in the atmosphere.
首先 较小的角度也会因为大气偏转削弱精度
Second, it affords more time for enemy interception.
其次 它会给敌方拦截提供更多的时间
A steep re-entry improves the missile's chances of avoiding interception
陡峭的再入能降低导弹被拦截的可能
and of reaching its target with minimum atmospheric deflection.
并使其在最小的大气偏转下到达目标
In this case or during the program is not the answer to the heat problem.
在这种情况下或在这项目中 热量的问题并没有被解决
Dr. Parameter must attack the problem of heat on the design front.
Parameter博士必须在设计方面解决热量问题
Logic would seem to indicate that fast travel requires a streamlined shape
逻辑貌似表明 高速的运动需要流线的轮廓
to slice its way through the air.
来切割空气
At subsonic velocities this is true.
在亚音速的速度 这是对的
But at supersonic speeds,
但在超音速的速度
a moving vehicle displaces air molecules which bounced off, forming a shockwave.
移动的飞行器使得空气分子被弹开 形成了冲击波
As speed increases the shock wave becomes more severe and heating increases.
随着速度的增加 冲击波变得更加猛烈 加热增加
An ICBM will have a free-fall re-entry speed in excess of 23,000 feet per second.
洲际弹道导弹自由落体的再入会达到每秒23000英尺 (7010m/s)
At this speed, the heat of molecular collision and friction, shearing of air molecules
在此速度下 分子碰撞和摩擦的热量 空气分子的剪切热量
is concentrated in a narrow zone along the surface of a streamlined vehicle.
集中在沿流线型飞行器表面的狭窄区域
The heat generated may cause the temperature to exceed 15000 degrees Fahrenheit.
所产生的热量可能导致温度超过15000华氏度 (8316℃)
To combat this terrific heat,
为了解决这大量的热量
Dr. Parameter designs instead a re-entry vehicle with a blunt frontal area.
Parameter博士转而设计钝头再入飞行器
The blunt shape creates its shockwave somewhat ahead of the vehicle.
钝形使得冲击波出现在飞行器前方
This occurs because the atmospheric molecules
这是因为大气分子
colliding with its frontal surface bounce back.
撞击其表面然后反弹
And intercept others coming in.
然后阻挡其他分子进入
Setting up a kind of picket line in advance of the warhead.
在弹头前建立一种警戒线
The peak heat is generated in this area away from the surface of the vehicle.
峰值热量生成在远离飞行器表面的这个位置
Although the blunt shape
虽然钝形
decreases the peak heating of the warhead to half that of a streamline shape,
比起流线形弹头只有一半的峰值热量
it will still heat up to 7,000 degrees Fahrenheit.
它仍然会升温到7000华氏度 (3871℃)
Much too hot for unprotected warhead structures.
对于没有保护的弹头结构而言还是太热
To further reduce heating,
为了进一步降低加热
Dr. Parameter must find other techniques in addition to the blunt shape.
Parameter博士必须找到钝形以外的其他技术
His first solution is the heatsink.
他的第一个解决方案是散热器
Use the blunt design and add a mass of heat conducting metal
运用钝形设计 并加入足够大的导热金属
large enough to absorb most of the heat generated during re-entry
以吸收大部分再入大气层时产生的热量
without melting before impact.
不会在撞击前熔化
It works, but he is not yet satisfied.
它成功了 但他并没有得到满足
The weight of the heatsink displaces more than one-fourth of the payload.
散热器超过有效载荷质量的四分之一
Furthermore the blunt designs slows the missile,
此外 钝形设计使导弹减速
keeping it in the atmosphere a longer time
让它在大气层中的时间更长
making it less accurate and easier to intercept.
使得它准确率下降 更容易被拦截
For the greatest accuracy and shortest time in the atmosphere,
为了达到最大精度和最短的大气内时间
Doc knows that the streamline shape is the best
博士知道 流线造型是最好的
but the heatsink cannot absorb and distribute the sudden extremely
但是散热器不能吸收分散
generated during the re-entry of a streamlined vehicle.
飞行器再入过程中快速产生的热量
Doc reasons, if the heat cannot be absorbed why not eject it as fast as it's generated?
博士推想 如果这些热量不能被吸收 为什么不以它被产生的速度排出它
The answer is ablation.
答案是烧蚀
Ablation!
烧蚀！
Coat the frontal surface of the streamline missile
在流线型导弹的头部覆盖薄薄的
with layers of a blade of material composed of fibres resins and ceramics.
由纤维树脂和陶瓷组成的复合材料层
This ablative coating protects the missile from the extreme heat in several ways.
这种烧蚀涂层从多个方面保护导弹免于极端热量
It is a poor heat conductor.
这是一种热的不良导体
Its surface gradually melts away taking heat with it.
它的表面逐渐熔化 带走热量
And it's vapor forms a thin insulating layer deflecting some of the heat from the surface.
而它的蒸气形成一层薄薄的绝缘层 将一些表面热量转移
The ablative principle combats the heat problem effectively.
烧蚀原理能够有效解决散热问题
and permits steeper re-entry angles while adding a minimum of weight.
同时在增加较小的重量下 允许更陡的再入角
The streamlined missile with its increased speed
流线型导弹增加的速度
affords the least possibility of interception and the greatest accuracy.
使其被拦截的可能性最小且达到的精度最高
It does produce a huge deceleration factor approaching 150 G's.
它确实产生接近150G的巨大减速系数
Fortunately this poses no threat to a warhead.
好在这种情况对弹头没有威胁
But for manned or other recovery missions, the G load is a most important factor.
但对于载人或其它返回式任务来说 G值是最重要的因素
For manned re-entry this force should be held below 10 G's.
对于载人再入而言应保持低于10个G的加速度
A shallow re-entry angle of about 1 to 5 degrees is the simple answer.
简单的答案是大约1至5度的浅再入角
The shallower the angle, the less the G load.
较浅角度 较小的加速度
But this will be sustained over a longer period of time.
但是 这会持续较长的一段时间
This means a longer time at high speed through the friction of the atmosphere.
这意味着需要更长的时间高速穿过大气层的摩擦
Let's take a moment to see why this is not desirable.
让我们来看看为什么这是不可取的
Dr. Parameter.
Parameter博士
Thank you.
谢谢
A gentleman we have here a kettle of water.
一位先生 我们这里有一锅水
Heathcliff, we can use you in this experiment.
Heathcliff 我们可以在这个实验中用到你
Oh boy an experiment.
天哪 一个实验
Thank you sir.
谢谢你 先生
Now if we may have another kettle of water.
现在 如果我们可以有另一锅水
And you're stand-in.
而你是替身
Thank you.
谢谢
Now we'll proceed with the experiment.
现在 我们继续进行实验
Experiment?
实验？
We'll add the same amount of fuel under each kettle.
我们在每个锅下添加相同的燃料
But alter the form of the fuel under one kettle.
但改变一个锅下燃料的形态
To make it burn faster.
让它燃烧得更快
We ignite both at the same time.
我们同时点燃两个
And compare the results.
并比较结果
Splendid.
非常好
I'd like to point out that the fast burning fuel although reaching its intensity quickly.
我想指出的是 快速燃烧的燃料 虽然很快达到其强度
Exhausted itself quickly.
很快耗尽本身
The heat absorbed was negligible.
吸收的热量可以忽略不计
The slow burning fuel on the other hand gradually increases its intensity.
在另一方面 缓慢燃烧的燃料逐渐增加其强度
It will generate the same total heat load
这将产生相同的总热负荷
but over a longer period of time
但是它通过一段较长的时间
and you'll notice more heat is absorbed.
你会发现更多的热量被吸收
Oh.
哦
Thank you Heathcliff.
谢谢你 Heathcliff
Thank you Dr. Parameter.
谢谢 Parameter博士
So although the peak heat generated in the shallow re-entry is less,
因此 尽管在浅再入产生的峰值热量更小
the capsule is in the heating regime for a longer time.
返回舱处于加热状态的时间更长
And without the utmost protection would absorb an intolerable amount of heat.
而它如果没有最大限度保护 将吸收无法承受的热量
For manned re-entry, Dr. Parameter overcomes the deceleration enemy
对于载人再入 Parameter博士通过浅角度程序
through program with the shallow angle.
克服减速问题
But he must combat heat on the design front.
但他必须在设计方面解决热量
A blunt shape to cause a detached shock wave.
钝形使冲击波分离
A picket line against heat.
警戒线应对热量
And ablative materials for additional heat control.
烧蚀材料作为额外的热量控制
The doc is confident his new design will fulfill the requirements.
博士自信于他的新设计能够满足要求
Now to try it out.
现在来尝试一下
He wants low peak deceleration so the shallow re-entry path is mandatory.
他想要低峰值减速 因此一定需要浅再入路径
This brings him down safely if a little off target.
如果稍微偏离目标 这使他安全降落
To achieve some control and accuracy as well as safety,
为了实现一定的可控和精度以及安全
Dr. Parameter has been working on other design concepts
Parameter博士一直致力于研究其他的设计理念
particularly shapes that produce lift.
特别是产生升力的形状
He knows that a ballistic missile is designed and programmed
他知道 弹道导弹的设计和编程
to hit a particular point on the Earth's surface.
是为了击中地球表面上的特定点
A manned ballistic vehicle with the same objective
具有相同目标的载人弹道飞行器
is much less accurate due to its design and long shallow penetration
由于它的设计和长距离浅再入 精度要低得多
but a lifting vehicle
但升力飞行器
which is capable of descending at a still more shallow angle
能够以更浅的角度下降
and with an extremely low deceleration rate is able to change direction.
并具有极低的减速率 且能够改变方向
This control gives it wide selectivity of landing sites within a large footprint area.
这种可控给予它降落地点宽泛的选择
For the shortest range within the footprint,
为了降落在尽可能近的范围内
the vehicle is pulled up into a maximum lift attitude at re-entry.
飞行器在再入过程中以最大升力姿态拉起
This induces maximum drag, causing a steeper, more abrupt descent.
这导致最大阻力 造成一个陡峭的斜坡下降
For the longest possible range,
为了尽可能远的范围
the vehicle must assume the attitude of maximum lift / drag ratio
飞行器必须采取最大升阻比的姿态
this footprint huge at first shrinks gradually as the vehicle descends.
这个开始很大的范围随着飞行器的下降逐渐缩减
Dr. Parameter while considering the advantages of lifting vehicles
Parameter博士在考虑升力体飞行器优势的同时
is also aware of their drawbacks.
也意识到它们的缺点
First the lifting structure itself imposes weight penalties.
首先升力体结构本身增加重量
which compete with the all-important matter of payload.
这与重要的有效载荷竞争
Then lifting vehicles may also spend up to 20 minutes in the heat regime
然后升力体飞行器也可能会处于受热状态长达20分钟
and being more streamlined they require a still more complex heat protection system
而为了更加流线 他们需要一个更复杂的热保护系统
competing still further with payload.
进一步与有效载荷竞争
Dr. Parameter with his associates has studied the strategy of atmospheric penetration.
Parameter博士和他的同事研究了大气进入的策略
He knows it's natural enemies, deceleration and heat.
他了解它的天敌 减速和热量
And has met them on the two fronts of program and design.
并在计划和设计两个方面解决它们
He has accomplished important objectives.
他已经完成了重要的目标
For the intercontinental ballistic missile,
对于洲际弹道导弹
the objectives are rapid atmospheric penetration and accuracy.
目标是快速大气穿透和准确性
The warheads natural enemy is sudden intense heat.
弹头的天敌是突如其来的强热
Its program high velocity, steep re-entry.
其方案是高速度 陡峭的再入
Its design streamlined with ablation to combat sudden heat.
其设计是通过流线型和烧蚀解决骤热
For a manned or other recovery mission the objectives are
对于载人或其它再入式任务的目标
first of all safety and then control.
首先是安全 然后是可控
The mission's natural enemies, high deceleration sustained Heat.
这些任务的天敌 高减速度和持续的热量
Its program shallow re-entry for low deceleration.
其方案是低减速浅再入
The vehicles design blunt.
这些飞行器的设计是 钝体
Yet with control capabilities, a maneuverable lifting shape.
然而有着可控能力 一个有机动性的升力体
The resulting long duration within the heat regime exacts a weight penalty.
长时间处于受热状态会导致重量的损失
Because a complex heat protection system is needed.
因为复杂的热保护系统是必要的
There will always be problems to solve.
总会有问题需要解决
Dr. Parameter has worked out successful compromises so far.
到目前为止Parameter博士已经摸索出成功的折衷方案
But he is still puzzling, still exploring.
但他仍然在苦思 仍在探索
He plucks his graphs, his curves and flings them boldly into space.
他拨弄着图表和曲线 大胆地把它们抛入太空
But he knows we have barely gotten our little toe into space.
但他知道 我们只是勉强把我们的小脚趾头送入宇宙
And he constantly seeks to improve that toe hold.
而他还在不断地寻求其上的改善
He must hold to the possible.
他必须坚守住可能的
Yet he constantly works along its impossible edges.
然而他也不断地沿着那不可能的边缘工作
He has opened the way for man's safe re-entry into the Earth's atmosphere.
他开辟了人类安全再入地球大气层的方式
Journey's end for space travel.
太空旅行的终点